是, 大臣  第2季第7集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译:claudia 校对&时间轴:tpring
忠诚问题
彼特 出版物规定第二稿周四前能交吧？
You'll have yourredraft on establishment levels by Thursday?
这么早就得交？
You need it that early?
我倒用不着那么早
I don't need it that early,
但大臣见特别委员会之前得先读一下
but the Ministerhas to read it before facing the select committee.
何况他还要记下来呢
What makes it harder, he has to remember it.
更何况他还得理解一下呢
Harderstill, he has to understand it.
对了 彼特 大臣的华盛顿演讲是你写的吗
Incidentally, did you write the Minister's Washington speech?
是啊 汉弗莱爵士
Yes, Sir Humphrey.
不错 写得不错     谢谢 汉弗莱爵士
Splendid. Well done. Thank you, Sir Humphrey.
大臣到办公室了
The Minister's in now.
好 谢谢大家
Good. Right, thank you all.
伯纳 大臣出差一周 你很幸福吧?
Have you enjoyed having your Ministeraway fora week?
说不上 有些工作不太好开展      是吗?
Not very much. Makes things very difficult.
哦 伯纳
Ah, Bernard
大臣不在根本就是天赐良机啊
A Minister's absence is a godsend
终于可以好好工作了
You can do the job properly foronce.
没他那些傻问题 灵机一动 整天操心报纸
No silly questions, no bright ideas, no fussing about the papers.
伯纳 我有时怀疑大臣不上报纸
I think our Minister doesn't believe he exists
就感觉不到自己的存在
unless he's in the papers.
我跟你赌 他回到办公室 第一句话就是
I'll bet the first thing he says is,
"我的华盛顿演讲有媒体报道吗"?
"Any reports on my Washington speech?"
赌多少?     一磅
Howmuch? A pound.
赌了 他不会问的 他已经问过了
Done. He won't because he's already asked
从机场回来的路上就问了
In the caron the way back from Heathrow.
有进步 伯纳 坐下吧
You're learning, Bernard. Sit down.
瞧见了吧 大臣不在还能让人进步
See why a Minister's absence is a good thing?
嗯 可工作积了这么多     这好说
Yes, but so much work piles up. There we are.
走之前请示几天 回来之后汇报几天
With a couple of days' briefing before and debriefing after
整整两周没他在这里碍手碍脚
he's out of ourhairfora fortnight.
接下来的半年 一旦他抱怨什么事没请示
Lfhe complains ofbeing uninformed,
就说那时他不在
say it came up while he was away.
所以才举行这么多高峰会议?
Hence so many summit conferences?
当然 这是我国立国之本啊
That's the only way the country works
把权力集中到10号 然后送首相去参加
Concentrate all the power at Number 10 then send the PM away
欧共体峰会 北约峰会 联邦峰会 什么都行
to EEC, NATO, Commonwealth summits, anywhere
内阁秘书才能好好管理国家啊
Then the Cabinet Secretary can run the country properly.
反正 我们现在就得见他
We ought to see him now.
你对彼特写的华盛顿演讲怎么看?
What do you think of the Washington speech?
"英国政府是忠诚高效的楷模"
"British administration as a model of loyalty and efficiency.
"严厉打击铺张浪费 彻底削减官僚主义"
A ruthless waron waste, cutting bureaucracy to the bone.
"全世界都可以借鉴英国"   能证明是真的吗?
Britain can teach the world" Can we prove it?
哦 伯纳 演讲之妙并不在于大臣说真话
A good speech isnt where we can prove he's telling the truth.
而在于没人能证明他撒谎
It's one in which nobody else can prove he's lying
但我还是...当然彼特写得很好 但我有点担心
But even so, I'm sure itwas good,
这场演讲 听众是否觉得太无聊了点
but I justwondered whether it was boring forthe audience.
当然无聊了
Of course itwas boring
无聊透顶啊
Bored the pants of them
要坐在那听完 简直就是恐怖      我以为...
Ghastly to have to sit through it, I should think
大臣的演讲不是写给听众的 伯纳
Ministers' speeches aren'twritten forthe audience.
不是吗?
Aren't they?
发表演讲只是例行公事 为了上报纸
Delivering a speech is just a formality to get into the papers.
不能考虑娱乐性 我们又不是编喜剧
We can'tworry about entertaining We're notwriting fora comedian
至少不是专业的
Well, not a professional one
重要的是该讲什么讲什么
The point is the speech said the right things.
那为什么要公开讲呢     这很重要
But why say it in public? It's vital.
白纸黑字印出来 大臣才会在委员会维护我们
Once printed, the Minister defend us in select committees.
他总会维护我们的吧     那是有限度的 伯纳
He defends us anyway. Well... only to a point, Bernard.
因为一旦出了差错
Once something goes wrong,
大臣首先想到的就是推在部属身上
the Minister's first instinct is to rat on his department.
所以演讲要印下来 让他站稳立场
We must nail his trousers to the mast.
您是说表明立场?     不 站稳立场
You mean nail his colours? No, his trousers.
省得他脚底抹油 走吧
Then he can't climb down Come on.
欢迎回来 大臣     你好 汉弗莱
Welcome home, Minister Hello, Humphrey.
伯纳 你不是说有关于我演讲的剪报吗?
Bernard, didn't you say there were press cuttings on my speech?
是的 大臣 我放在盒子里了
Yes, I put them in the box, Minister.
大臣 您知道明天委员会的听证至关重要吧
Minister, you do realise the importance of tomorrow's hearing?
可不是 媒体都会在场
Indeed. The press will be there.
不仅仅是媒体的问题 大臣
It's notjust a question of the press.
这是要审查本部的未来工作
It's a scrutiny of this department's future operation.
要是我们表现得铺张浪费 或者玩忽职守
If it emerged thatwe were extravagant or incompetent...
我们有铺张浪费或者玩忽职守吗?     当然没有
Are we extravagant or incompetent? Of course not.
但委员会里有人心怀不轨 特别是德贝郡那位
But there are hostile members especially one for Derbyshire.
天 贝蒂·欧汉不会来吧?     唉 是的
No Betty Oldham won't be there? Yes, alas.
请您先牢记这份简报 大臣 有问题就问我
I urge you to masterthis brief and ask if you have any problems.
又是简报? 回来的飞机上我刚记住一份
Anotherbrief? I've only just mastered one.
是吗? 讲什么的?
Really? Whatwas in it?
记不住了
I can't remember.
坐飞机没法集中注意力 又是饮料又是电影的
Difficult to concentrate on a plane, all those drinks
打个瞌睡也要被吵醒     当然 大臣
And they wake you up. Of course, Minister.
您醒着确实不容易集中注意力
Frightfully difficult to concentrate if you keep being woken up.
说真的 就这一份简报
Seriously, this is the only brief
概括了人家会问的问题
with possible questions from the committee
非常谨慎适当地阐述了我们的立场
with appropriate answers carefully presented to give ourposition.
绝对精确吗?
Is it absolutely accurate?
谨慎而适当 阐述了我们的立场
They're carefully presented to give ourposition.
你说委员会很重要 不能显得我在误导他们
I cannot be seen to mislead them.
不会显得您在误导他们的
You will not be seen to mislead them.
都是事实?     只有事实
The truth? And nothing but.
全部事实?     当然不是
The whole truth? Of course not.
就说我们有所保留?     绝对不行
We tell them we keep secrets? Indeed not
为什么不行?
Why not?
"保守秘密的人必须同时保守"
"He thatwould keep a secret must keep it secret,
"他有秘密这个秘密"
that he hath the secret to keep".
这话谁说的?
Who said that?
那是汉弗莱爵士
Itwas Sir Humphrey.
谁首创的?     弗朗西斯·培根 对吧
Who said it originally? Francis Bacon, wasn't it?
哦 对
Oh, yes.
怎么大臣不管干嘛都有简报?
Why can'twe go anywhere without briefs?
以免到时穿帮
In case they get caught with theirtrousers down.
穿帮? 补起来嘛
Trousers down Pick them
很好笑 伯纳
Very droll, Bernard.
等会还有别的事吗?     您今天没有别的日程
Are we going to be interrupted? Yourdiary's empty today.
好吧 提醒我 那篇东西讲了什么?
Whatwas in that submission I read?
或多或少和去年的报告差不多
More or less a rehash of last year's report.
前年的? 再前一年呢?      都是 大臣
And the yearbefore? And the yearbefore that?
从1867年以来就没变过
Yes, eversince 1867.
只有些修饰润色而已 我们来看一遍吧?
With appropriate alterations. Shall we go through it?
非得看吗? 我时差还没倒过来呢
Mustwe? I'm still jet-lagged.
随便您 大臣 不过媒体都会到场的
All the press will be there.
对 还是来看看吧
Right, let's get down to it.
实际上 主席先生 行政事务部
The fact is that the Department of Administrative Affairs
可靠而高效地提供了
is run to a high standard of efficiency and supports and services
政府所需一切行政工作
the administrative work of all Government departments,
这点在部门报告中已经说明
as we've said in oursubmission.
谢谢 大臣 大家有什么问题吗?
Thank you, Minister. Questions?
欧汉女士?    谢谢主席
Mrs Oldham? Thank you.
大臣 您知道麦肯·罗德吗?
Minister, have you heard of Malcolm Rhodes?
不知道
No.
罗德曾任行政部助理秘书 于去年辞职
He was assistant secretary in DAA until he resigned last year.
行政部共有23000人
There are 23,000 people in the DAA.
对 而他辞职了 或者被悄悄免职了
But he resigned orwas eased out.
之后去美国做管理顾问 最近他写了本书
Became a management consultant and has justwritten a book,
这是书的校样
this is an advance proof,
其中揭露了英国公务员惊人的浪费行为
he makes astounding allegations of waste of public money,
尤其在贵部门
particularly in yourdepartment.
主席先生 我能和我的助手讨论一下吗?
Could I have a word with my officials, MrChairman?
知道这回事吗?     没听说还有书啊
Know about this? Not about the book.
罗德是谁?     麻烦精 不可靠
Who is Rhodes? He's a trouble-maker.
书里讲了什么?     不知道
What's in the book? Don't know.
那我怎么办?     打岔
What do I do? Stall.
什么打岔?      所谓打岔就是回避问题
"Stall", meaning avoiding answer.
我知道什么叫打岔
Yes, I knowwhat stall means
你连伞也不给我一把就推我进了台风眼
You've sent me into a typhoon without even an umbrella
台风中伞没有用 风会把...
An umbrella's no use in wind...
闭嘴 伯纳
Shut up, Bernard
您和助手讨论完了吗?
Have you had sufficient consultation with yourofficials?
我...
I...
我来读读罗德先生揭露的不良现象
Let me read you some scandalous facts Mr Rhodes reveals,
原文如下 "赫里福郡4号补给站"
and I quote, "No 4 supply depot in Herefordshire,
"有2间飞机修理库 现为仓库"
two formeraircraft hangars used only forstores
"也由中央空调昼夜保持70度(21℃)"
but which are centrally-heated to 70 degrees day and night".
您有何解释?     这种细节问题需要事先查证
What do you say about that? I can't answerwithout priornotice.
不过有可能是真的     是真的 我上周查过了
It might not be true. It is. I checked.
如此铺张浪费 能有什么理由?
What reason can there be forsuch appalling extravagance?
要看存的是什么 有些材料不耐寒
Some materials deteriorate, depending on what it is.
铜质电线
Copperwire.
是啊...铜质电线?
Yes, well... copperwire?
潮湿时可能生锈
It can corrode in damp conditions.
包塑胶皮的
It's plastic-coated.
塑胶皮
Plastic-coated?
我...
I...
塑胶皮? 我会调查的
Plastic-coated? I'll certainly have it looked into.
他还说 贵部坚持集中采购钢笔 铅笔 回形针
He says you ordering all pens, paperclips and so on centrally
然后按各部门的需求发放
then distributing them against departmental requisitions.
情有可原 批发能节约成本啊
That seems to be quite sensible. Savings through bulk purchase.
据他论证 这样做的实际支出比职员
He demonstrates that this is fourtimes more expensive
自己去大街上买还贵4倍
than if officers bought what they want on the High Street.
挺有趣的
Very interesting.
果真如此 我们就改革 我们并非顽固的官老爷
If so, we'll change the system. We're not a rigid bureaucracy.
他说他在职期间提过这个建议
He proposed this change when he was in yourdepartment,
但大家安于现状 把它否决了
it was turned down, people were used to the existing procedure
这不是"顽固的官老爷'吗?     我会调查的
How's that forrigid bureaucracy? I'll have it looked into.
会调查?     对
"Looked into"? Yes
上周你的华盛顿演讲中提到
You said in yourWashington speech lastweek
你们部厉行节约 可谓世界楷模
that you conducted a waron waste, teach the world a lesson.
那又如何解释你们花费75000磅建造
How do you reconcile thatwith spending ?5,000 on a roof garden
凯特灵津贴办公室的楼顶花园呢?
on top of the supplementary benefits office in Kettering?
我...我会...
I'm... I'll...
会调查?     对 我会的
Have it looked into? Yes Yes, I will
主席先生 行政部常任秘书下周出席委员会
The DAA's Permanent Secretary is due to appearnextweek.
他来回答不是正好吗?
Isn't he the appropriate person to answerthe questions?
谢谢 通知汉弗莱爵士
Thank you. See that Sir Humphrey's notified.
也许您也该让他看看这些指责?
Perhaps you might let him see the allegations?
"为浪费公款辩白"? "行政大哉问"?
"Allegations of Governmentwaste"? "Big questions to answer"?
大臣 您让我进退两难     那我呢?
You've put me in a difficult position What about me?
首相要求节约 人家都在节约 就我们在浪费
The PM's demanding economies, we wast all this money
大臣 没人真的在节约 您该知道吧
No one's been saving anything, you should know that
但他们样子做得很好啊
They look as though they have.
您不能打岔吗?     什么打岔?
Couldn't you have stalled? Stalled?
转移焦点
Blurred things a bit.
您最会转移焦点啊     什么?
You're good at blurring the issue. What?
您有卓越的才华 能让状况难以理解 大臣
You have a considerable talent formaking things unintelligible.
你说什么     不不 我这是夸您
I beg yourpardon I mean that as a compliment.
转移焦点是大臣的基本技能之一
Blurring the issue is one of the basic ministerial skills.
还有哪些?
And the others?
拖延决策 回避问题
Delaying decisions, dodging questions,
玩弄数据 歪曲事实 掩盖错误
juggling figures, bending facts and concealing errors.
我该做什么?
Whatwas I to do?
做个样子 实际上什么也不做
Make it look like you'd do something and do nothing.
就像您以前做的一样
Like you usually do.
可如果指责是真的...      很好 大臣 "如果"
But if these revelations are true... Exactly, Minister, "if".
您可以谈真伪问题
You could have discussed truth.
委员会才不关心事情真伪
The committee isn't interested in truth.
他们都是国会议员
They're all MPs
安全问题呢?     铅笔算哪门子安全问题?
What about a security matter? HB pencils a security matter?
这要看铅笔写了些什么
Depends what you write with them
办公楼上干吗建花园?
Why build roof gardens on top of offices?
我们用了一家美国公司的设计图
We took overthe office design from an American company,
碰巧没人发现屋顶上有花园
it happens that nobody noticed the roof gardens on the plan
天哪
God
犯了点小错 人之常情嘛
It's a tiny mistake anyone could make.
75000磅叫小错? 那什么叫大错?
Tiny mistake, ?5,000? Give me an example of a big mistake?
让人发现了就叫大错
Letting people find out about it
放电线的棚子干吗开暖气?
Why are we heating sheds full of wire?
您要听真话?     要是不麻烦的话
You want the truth? Lf it's no trouble.
员工利用这个棚养蘑菇
The staff are using the sheds forgrowing mushrooms.
禁止掉
Stop them
他们从1945年就这么做了
They've been doing it since 1945.
养蘑菇是这份无聊工作的唯一消遣
It's the only perk in an extremely boring job.
罗德的文具采购提案为什么不理?
What about Rhodes's proposals forstationery?
他是个麻烦精 变态地迷恋效率
A trouble-makerand crank unhealthily obsessed with efficiency.
为什么不采纳他的提案? 能省几百万呢
Why didn'twe adopt his proposals and save millions?
对 但要做很多前期工作     所以呢?
Yes, but a lot of work to implement. So?
需要更多员工     汉弗莱
Taking on more staff. Humphrey
提出反证?     我哪来反证
Disprove it. I can't, obviously.
可不是     你编的?
Exactly Making it up?
当然     为什么?
Of course. Why?
演示如何对付特委会
As an example ofhow to handle a select committee.
这些都很好 汉弗莱爵士 谈细节吧
Sir Humphrey, let's get down to details.
比如那个开暖气的飞机棚     没错
This heated aircraft hangar. Indeed.
我明白委员会的顾虑
I do understand yourconcern,
但是你看 赫里福郡冬天极其寒冷
but it gets frightfully cold in Herefordshire.
即使公务员...     那里头不是公务员
Even civil servants... We aren't talking about civil servants.
是一大堆铜线 有塑胶皮保暖
We're talking coils of wire plastic-coated to keep them warm
总有员工进进出出     为什么?
Staff are in and out all the time. Why?
提货 退货 盘货
Taking deliveries, making withdrawals, checking records,
防火检查...
fire inspections...
他们可以戴手套吧?     但这是员工福利政策
They can weargloves? But it's a staff welfare policy.
这项政策花了纳税人几百万磅
I suggest this policy is costing the taxpayermillions
没话说了 汉弗莱爵士?
Nothing to say?
我无权评论国家政策 去问大臣
I can't comment on Government policy.
但你为大臣提建议
But you advise the Minister.
主席当然理解 我不能泄漏我的建议
I can't disclose how I advise him.
大臣对政策负责     好 我们会问大臣
The Minister's responsible forpolicy. We'll ask the Minister.
文具的事怎么说呢?
What about stationery savings?
那会使基层职员掌握大笔公款
Itwould've meant Government patronage on junior staff.
大笔公款?
"Considerable Government patronage"?
一包回形针的钱?
Buying a packet of paperclips?
国家政策要求对公款使用人数
It's Government policy to exercise strict control
实施严格控制 相信您也理解
overwho can spend its money.
谁要用回形针 谁自己去买 这是常理
It's common sense to let people buy theirown paperclips.
政府政策和常理无关
Government policy is nothing to do with common sense.
你不觉得政策应该改改吗?
Don't you think it's time the policy was changed?
嗯 汉弗莱爵士?
Well, Sir Humphrey?
我无权评论国家政策 问大臣吧
I can't comment on Government policy. Ask the Minister.
大臣建议我们问你
The Ministeradvises us to ask you.
我建议你们问大臣
I'm advising you to ask the Minister.
要绕到几时啊?     你说完事就完事
When does this end? As soon as you like.
好 说说屋顶花园吧
Let's come to the roof garden.
好 很荣幸
Yes, with pleasure.
它隶属于一系列屋顶隔热装置
This was part of a wide variety of roof insulation schemes,
这是政府的节能实验
which the Governmentwas testing in fuel economy.
花了75000磅
But ?5,000
本打算用卖花卉蔬菜的钱抵销成本的
Itwas thought the sale of vegetable might offset the cost.
结果呢?
And did it?
不能抵消     那干吗还留着它?
No. Then why not abandon the garden?
造也造好了 正好隔热用 下不为例
It's there now insulating the roof. we aren't building any more
但已经浪费了75000磅
But you've wasted ?5,000
政策要求尝试一切节能手段啊
All proposals were tested forfuel saving.
这样浪费纳税人的钱也在所不惜?
At this fantastic waste of taxpayers' money?
你同意这是浪费吧?
You agree itwas wasted?
我无权评论国家政策 去问大臣
I can't comment on Government policy. Ask the Minister.
汉弗莱爵士 我们问大臣什么
Look, whateverwe ask the Minister,
他都说是行政问题 归你管
he says is a question foryou.
我们问你 你又说是政策问题 问大臣
Whateverwe ask you, you say is a question forthe Minister
这叫我们怎么调查?
How do we find out what's going on?
对对 我能理解你们的难处
Yes, I see there is a dilemma here.
就是说 尽管政府认为大臣负责政策
Government regards policy as the responsibility of Ministers
部属负责行政
and administration as the responsibility of officials,
可一旦涉及行政政策 就会混淆
questions of administrative policy cause confusion
行政的政策制定和政策的行政执行
between policy of administration and administration of policy
尤其在归责问题上 行政的政策制定
especially when responsibility forthe policy of administration
与政策的行政执行产生了矛盾
conflicts with the policy of administration of policy.
这些都是胡扯
That's a load of meaningless drivel.
对吧?
Isn't it?
我无权评论国家政策 去问大臣
I can't comment on Government policy. Ask the Minister.
多亏你了 汉弗莱
A great help
别客气 大臣 我尽力而为嘛
I did my best.
尽力保你自己吧 你说了等于没说
Best foryourself, perhaps But youranswers solved nothing.
别忘了 后天我们要同时出席第三次质询
We'll both be there getting the third degree from the committee
得说得过去才行 口径一致
We've got to have the same answers
来确定一下立场吧     好 事实是什么?
Let's establish ourposition. What are the facts?
我在说立场 跟事实无关
The facts are neitherhere northere
好吧 立场是什么?
I see. What's ourposition?
我们有五个标准理由
We choose one of the five standard excuses
每个应付一项指责 最好不重样
to deal with each allegation.
五个标准理由?      对
Five standard excuses?
第一个理由曾在剑桥间谍案中使用过
First, the excuse we used in the Anthony Blunt case:
"这些事都有合理解释"
"There's an explanation foreverything,
"但出于安全考虑 不能公开"
but security forbids its disclosure".
第二个理由曾在综合中学辩论中使用过
Second, the excuse we used forcomprehensive schools:
"由于降低了预算"
"Because ofbudget cuts,
"监管力量削弱才有了这一疏忽"
supervisory resources went beyond their limits".
不是真的吧?     但这个借口很好用
That's not true, is it? But it's a good excuse.
第三个曾在协和飞机事件中使用过
Then there's the excuse forConcorde:
"该实验值得一做 并且已经停止"
"Aworthwhile experiment, now abandoned,
"得到了大量珍贵数据 还提供了就业"
but it had provided much valuable data and employment".
这是真的吧?
But that is true, isn't it?
哦 当然不是
Oh, no, of course it isn't.
第四个 慕尼黑协议的理由
Four, there's the excuse forthe Munich Agreement:
"有些重要信息 定局之后我们才得知"
"It occurred before important facts were known
"下不为例"
and couldn't re-occur".
什么重要信息?
What important facts?
希特勒其实想征服欧洲
That Hitlerwanted to conquer Europe.
这谁不知道     外交部的人不知道
I thought everybody knew that Not the Foreign Office.
第五呢?     第五
Five? Five...
克里米亚轻骑兵溃败的理由
The Charge of the Light Brigade excuse:
"由个人决策失误引起"
"An unfortunate lapse by an individual,
"已根据内部纪律条例予以处理"
dealtwith under internal disciplinary procedures".
就这几条 都能搞定?     走运的话 基本没问题
That covers everything? Just about, so far.
连战争也行?     小型战争吧
Even wars? Small wars.
从现在起我们要紧密合作     合则强 不合则亡
It's teamwork from now on. United we stand, divided we fall
大臣 您10分钟内得到下院
Minister, you're due at the House.
首相顾问斯宾塞爵士请您今天去喝一杯
PM's adviserwants you to pop in fora drink. Sir Mark Spencer.
斯宾塞?     我提议5点半
Mark Spencer? I suggested 5.30?
好 天啊 我就知道有麻烦
Fine, yes. Oh, dear. I knew there'd be trouble.
首相要问 为什么我们对质询回答不力
The PM wants to knowwhy ourreplies have been so feeble.
也可能就是喝一杯 大臣
Perhaps it's just fora drink.
别傻了 10号里喝一杯从来不是解渴用的
They don't ask you fora drink just because you're thirsty
6点半我们再碰头 编个故事出来
I'll meet you back here at 6.30, and we'll cook up a story.
是确定立场 大臣     我就这个意思
Agree ourposition, Minister. That's what I said.
请进
Come in
你好 吉姆
Hello, Jim.
威士忌?     好的 谢谢
Scotch? Thanks.
你情况怎样?     还可以
How are things going? Fine.
说到特委会 那本书确实始料未及
That select committee was a shock, throwing the book at us,
但一切还在掌握中 我和汉弗莱会给出说法的
but everything's undercontrol. Humphrey and I can explain it.
首相不必担心
The PM shouldn'tworry.
真不知道罗德从哪得到这么多内幕
I'd like to knowwhere Malcolm Rhodes got all his information.
也不知道书稿又怎么到了欧汉手里
And who gave the proofs to Betty Oldham?
首相肯定气坏了
The PM must be livid.
不过这可不能怪我
It's no fault of mine.
为什么你觉得首相会生气?     肯定的嘛
Why do you think the PM's livid? Surely?
我们用常理分析一下吧 吉姆 坐下
Let's look at the situation logically. Sit down.
当然
Yes. Of course.
我先问你几件事
Let me ask you some questions.
在公共支出方面 首相有何意图?
What is the PM trying to achieve in public expenditure?
当然要削减     为什么成果不彰呢?
Cuts, obviously. Why so little success?
公务员不配合?     所有大臣都想削减支出吗?
Obstruction from the service? All the Cabinet committed to it?
是吧 至少我是     没错 但谁都削不下来
I think so. I certainly am. But no Minister's made any cuts.
循序渐进 不能心急嘛     不对
Rome wasn't built in a day. No.
问题在于 大臣都被驯服了
It's because all the Ministers have gone native.
不是吧?     公务员调教了他们
Surely? The civil service has trained them
也许有一两个吧 不过我可没有
Well, maybe true... Certainly not of me
如果一名大臣真想削减支出
If a Ministerwere really trying to cut expenditure,
他对一本揭露政府浪费的书 会作何反应?
howwould he react to a book exposing Governmentwaste?
我觉得他会...      嗯?
I should think he'd... Mmm?
这个要看...
Itwould depend...
你到底想说什么?
What are you trying to say?
知道公务员怎么说你吗? 他们说与你合作愉快
Knowwhat the civil service say? You're a pleasure to work with.
噢
Oh
噢...
Oh...
驯兽师屋豪就是这么说她的哈巴狗的
That's what Barbara Woodhouse says about herspaniels.
汉弗莱爵士甚至说你是无价之宝
Sir Humphrey said you're worth yourweight in gold.
你觉得这怎么讲?
What does that suggest to you?
是说我彻底失败了?
That I've failed utterly?
你还得来杯威士忌
You look as if you need anotherScotch.
首相不高兴
The PM isn't pleased
是因为我在特委会面前
with my performance at the committee.
没能掩盖我们的失误     恰恰相反
I failed to coverup the failure. On the contrary.
他不满意你掩盖得太成功了
He's not pleased because you're covering up too well.
你没发现吗? 你在掩护公务员 掩护汉弗莱
Don't you see? You're protecting the civil service.
首相和我千方百计
The PM and I are doing ourbest
揭露无法削减支出的原因
to expose why cuts in expenditure are not taking place.
你在帮公务员对抗政府
And you are helping the civil service to defy the Government.
我有吗?
Am I?
你想不通欧汉哪来的书稿
You were wondering where Betty Oldham got the proofs
罗德哪来的内幕消息
and where Malcolm Rhodes got that inside information.
猜猜看?
Can't you guess?
你是说...首相?
You mean... the PM?
当然不是
Of course not
不是直接的
Not directly.
你?
You mean... you?
到底要我跟特委会说什么?
What am I to do at the select committee?
你现在只有一条路可走 绝对忠诚
There's only one course open to you. Absolute loyalty.
忠于谁?
Who to?
这就看你了
That's yourdecision.
我们得知某些重要事实之前 大错已经铸成
Itwas an errorthat occurred before important facts were known.
我保证 这种疏忽下不为例
It is an oversight that couldn't possibly happen again.
大臣 您说是吧?     汉弗莱爵士完全正确
Wouldn't you agree, Minister? Perfectly correct.
官方回答正是这样
The correct official reply.
但我几天来一直在深思
But I've been thinking very deeply overthe last few days,
毫无疑问 特委会说到了点子上
and there's no doubt that this committee is on to something.
浪费当然存在
Of course there's waste.
这些案例各有各的借口
And excuses can always be found in individual cases.
但经你们一说 我认识到我们错了
But you have convinced me ourapproach is wrong.
大臣及其公务员老是在掩盖问题 互相辩解
Ministers and theircivil servants so often coverup and defend
其实发现和消灭问题才是正途
where they should seek out and destroy.
我和罗德先生 这本宝贵的书的作者谈过
I've spoken to Mr Rhodes, authorof this invaluable book,
他同意主持一次独立调查
and he'll head an independent enquiry
研究政府执政问题 首先从我部开刀
into the field of administration, starting with my department.
汉弗莱爵士有何反应?
And how does Sir Humphrey react to this?
汉弗莱爵士与我同心同德
Sir Humphrey is in complete agreementwith me.
分工合作 是吧汉弗莱 我得说 我和他合作愉快
We work as a team. I must say, he's a pleasure to work with.
可是大臣 揭露出的事
But this account of what's been going on
和你在华盛顿说的"严厉打击浪费"互相矛盾啊
doesn't square with your speech about a waron waste.
我是个老派的人 贝蒂
Well, I'm an old-fashioned sort of chap, Betty,
我信仰一种叫做"忠诚"的东西
and I believe in a thing called loyalty.
内部矛盾内部解决 不可外扬 对吧 汉弗莱?
Whateveryou say in private you defend in public, eh, Humphrey?
这样的话 你现在不就不忠诚了吗?
In that case, aren't you being disloyal now?
非也 我认为大臣的忠诚水准更高
No. I believe a Minister has a higher loyalty.
效忠国会 效忠国家
A loyalty to Parliament and the nation.
为这种高于一切的忠诚
And that loyalty must be paramount,
他必须披荆斩棘 一往无前
howeverhard and painful that may be.
我当然要忠于我的部门和部属
Of course, one is loyal to one's department and officials,
只要证据允许 但我要公开表明我的一贯态度
until the evidence is overwhelming, but I must say in public,
改革可行 并即将进行
that reforms can and will take place,
相信汉弗莱爵士必将成为我忠诚的战友
and I know I shall find in Sir Humphrey my staunchest ally.
对吧 汉弗莱?
Isn't that so, Humphrey?
是的 大臣
Yes, Minister.
多亏您了 大臣     我尽力而为
A big help I did my best.
尽力保您自己吧 这就是您的"团结"? 可笑
The best foryourself This is your idea of teamwork? Amusing
我必须这么做     必须怎么做?
I had to do it. Had to do what?
主动向特委会检讨一切?
Cravenly admit everything to them?
您不知道我们要遭殃了吗?
Don't you realise how calamitous this is forus?
不会都遭殃吧 我希望      没希望的 大臣
Not both of us, I hope. You hope in vain.
部员们全副武装 没人还信任您
We're up in arms, with very little confidence in you.
至于10号 我都不敢想
As for Number 10, I shudderto think
对您的公开检讨 首相会作何反应
how the PM will react to yourpublic admission of failure.
首相写来的私人信件
A personal letter from the Prime Minister.
我警告过您了 大臣
I did warn you, Minister.
伯纳 你可以考虑为大臣
Bernard, you should give some thought
拟一封体面的辞呈了
to drafting a face-saving letter of resignation forthe Minister.
"亲爱的吉姆"
"Dear Jim..."
"亲爱的吉姆"?
"Dear Jim"?
"我们最近没能常常见面"
"We haven't seen enough of each other lately.
"你周日有空来我乡间别墅用个午餐吗?"
Are you free for lunch at Chequers on Sunday?
"家庭聚餐 带上老婆孩子 期待你的到来"
We shall just be the family. I look forward to seeing you".
我不明白...?
I don't think I?
有回报了 有回报了
It has paid off
阴谋 和斯宾塞喝酒的那一次
A conspiracy That drink with Mark Spencer
"常常见面...乡间别墅午餐..."
"...not seen enough... Lunch at Chequers..."
看 还是手写的 你知道值多少钱吗?
It's hand-written Do you realise howmuch it's worth?
现价好像是30枚银币(犹大出卖耶稣的价钱)
I believe the going rate is thirty pieces of silver
不 汉弗莱 忠诚和正直得到了应有的回报
No. Loyalty and integrity have received theirjust rewards.
忠诚?
Loyalty?
汉弗莱 我支持你 就像你一贯支持我的那样
I have backed you up as you have always backed me up
不是吗?
Isn't that so?
不好意思 你说什么?
Sorry? Did you say something?
我想他说的是 "是 大臣"
I think he said, "Yes, Minister".